Good morning. Today is February 3rd. It is the 24th of שבט.
Shevat. My name is Dan Margulis. I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer
and we will start today about halfway down נ"א ע"ב. Nun Aleph
Amud Bet. The discussion towards the end of yesterday's דף Daf was
about this מחלוקת Machlokes between רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov and רבנן Rabanan about under which cases could a person force
someone to take a שבועה Shvuah in some of these cases that
we've been dealing with, and the question of כמשיב אבידה KeMeishiv Aveidah
and is it for a minor or not, the question of a
minor being able to force someone to take a שבועה. Shvuah. There's
an interesting מחלוקת ראשונים Machlokes Rishonim about which שבועות Shvuot does that
exemption apply to. Does it apply only in cases of a שבועת
עד אחד, Shvuas Ed Echad, like if one witness is forcing the
שבועה, Shvuah, or there's three different שבועות Shvuos that could be involved:
שבועת עד אחד, Shvuas Ed Echad, one עד Ed claims or testifies
that you owe a certain debt, so then you can't actually extract
the debt but you have one witness, so that forces you to
take a שבועה; Shvuah; the second kind of שבועה Shvuah to be
concerned with would be שבועת הפקדון, Shvuas Hapikadon, if you're someone watching
over property, then and there's something goes wrong, so then the שומר
Shomer could be forced to take a שבועה Shvuah that he didn't
mess up; and then the third kind of שבועה Shvuah that we
would be concerned with here would be שבועת מודה במקצת, Shvuas Modeh
Bemiktzas, if a person admits to partial partial debt and then the
other part of the debt you then be forced to take a
שבועה Shvuah about. That's what we're going to read about now. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא כדרבה קמיפלגי. Ella KeRabba KamiPalgi. So this
מחלוקת Machlokes is actually about what רבה Rabbah said. דאמר רבה מפני
מה אמרה תורה מודה במקצת הטענה ישבע. DeAmar Rabbah Mipnei Mah Amrah
Torah Modeh BeMiktzas HaTa'anah Yishave'a. Why does the תורה Torah require someone
who agrees to a partial debt, that is, someone comes and says
you owe me $100 and the נטען Nitan says back, no, no,
no, I only owe you $50, or I only owe you $5,
that's מודה במקצת הטענה, Modeh BeMiktzas HaTa'anah, you're agreeing to or admitting
to part of the claim. So the הלכה מדאורייתא Halacha MiDeOraisa is
that a מודה במקצת Modeh BeMiktzas has to take a שבועה. Shvuah.
So רבה Rabbah says, what is the rationale? It's interesting to suggest
like why would רבה Rabbah even have to be suggesting this, who
cares what the reason is if it's הלכה, Halacha, it's הלכה. Halacha.
So רבה Rabbah is still saying, מפני מה אמרה תורה מודה במקצת
הטענה ישבע. Mipnei Mah Amrah Torah Modeh BeMiktzas HaTa'anah Yishave'a. The rationale
is going to become important in determining how this question of מודה
במקצת Modeh BeMiktzas applies to our מחלוקת Machlokes between רבי אליעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov and רבנן. Rabanan. So חזקה אין אדם
מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו. Chazakah Ain Adam Meiz Panav Bifnei Ba'al
Chovo.
We have a חזקה, Chazakah, general חזקה Chazakah that a person is
not going to brazenly, blatantly contradict someone outright, look in רש"י, Rashi,
not רש"י, Rashi, look in תוספות Tosfos actually, it's an interesting claim,
אין אדם מעיז כל מקום שאותו כנגדו יודע שהוא משקר. Ain Adam
Meiz Kol Makom SheOso KeNegdo Yode'a SheHu Meshaker. If the person opposite
you, the person you're claiming against knows you're lying, no one is
that brazen. So it's interesting to suggest, you know, it's a big
question whether some of these חזקות Chazakos in the גמרא Gemara still
apply, whether people's psychology changes, people's personality changes, etc. Some people might
make a suggestion maybe this rationale doesn't apply anymore, nonetheless, this is
a הלכה דאורייתא, Halacha DeOraisa, so this still principle this still principle
of מודה במקצת Modeh BeMiktzas would still apply for sure. אין אדם
מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו והאי בכוליה בעי למכפריה ליה והאי דלא
כפריה משום דאין אדם מעיז פניו בפני בעל חובו. Ain Adam Meiz
Panav Bifnei Ba'al Chovo VeHai BeKuleih Ba'ei LeMichpreih Lei VeHai DeLo Kafreih
Mishum DeAin Adam Meiz Panav Bifnei Ba'al Chovo. So really he would
therefore, the fact that he has a חזקה Chazakah to tell the
truth, he should have admitted to the entire debt. How come he's
not admitting to the entire debt? Because ובכוליה דלא לודה ליה והאי
דלא אודי ליה דמשתמוטי הוא דקמשתמיט ליה. UvKuleih DeLo Lodeh Lei VeHai
DeLo Odei Lei DeMishtamutei Hu DeKaMishtamit Lei.
He was trying to push him off, he's trying to delay paying
back this loan, buying some time. וסבר ליה עד דהוו לי זוזי
ופרענא ליה. VeSavar Lei Ad DeHavu Li Zuzi UFarna Lei. He's going
to say, I don't have all the money now, so I'm going
to try to delay, I'll say I only owe $50 now, so
then I'll pay him $50 now, and then I'll come back six
months later once I've saved up and I'll be able to pay
the other half later. So that's the rationale behind a person who
wants to tell the truth, wants to pay back the loan, is
an honest person fundamentally but needs an extension and is trying to
use the mechanism of מודה במקצת Modeh BeMiktzas to force a delay
in paying back the loan and therefore the תורה Torah imposed upon
such a person a שבועה Shvuah to say that's dishonest, that's illegal
to try to extend the loan against against the lender's will. If
you can't pay now, he's going to be able to extract property
from your from your real estate and things like that. ואמר רחמנא
רמי שבועה עליה. VeAmar Rachmana Remei Shvuah Aleih. היכי דליודה ליה בכוליה.
Heichi DeLyodeh Lei BeKuleih. The תורה Torah imposes this שבועה Shvuah as
if to encourage or to push someone to actually be able to
admit to the entire loan. ורבי אליעזר בן יעקב סבר לא שנא
בו ולא שנא בבנו. VeRabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov Savar Lo Shna Bo
VeLo Shna BiVno. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says
it doesn't matter whether it's the person himself who lent the money
and now you're responding to him or whether it's his heir, the
you're dealing with the child. אינו מעיז. Eino Meiz. Rabbi Elazar Ben
Yaakov says it doesn't matter whether it's the person himself who lent
the money and now you're responding to him or whether it's his
heir, you're dealing with the child. אינו מעיז Eino me'iz and you're
not going to then stand up against this child. Now you might
say the rationale makes a little bit less sense and that's exactly
why there's a מחלוקת machlokes because there's less of a psychological impediment
if it's not really the person you actually made the original transaction
with. הלכך Hilkakh לאו Lav משיב אבידה הוא, meshiv aveidah hu. ורבנן
סברי verabbanan savrei בו bo דאינו מעיז de'eino me'iz
אבל aval לבנו livno מעיז. me'iz. But a person will stand up
against this child, the child who wasn't actually part of the original
transaction. The רבנן Rabbanan שיטה shitta is therefore that מודה במקצת, modeh
bemiktzas, the psychological pressure isn't there, and so a person would be
מעיז פניו me'iz panav and would deny the entire thing. So the
fact that you're מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzas means that we have more
of a reason to trust you. ומשום דלא מעיז U'mishum delo me'iz
משיב אבידה meshiv aveidah הוא. hu, And therefore we give you more
the benefit of the doubt, we don't force you to take a
שבועה, shvuah, it's like משיב אבידה. meshiv aveidah. You're being such a
nice, wonderful, honest person. Okay, let's continue with the next משנה mishnah
right at the top of נב עמוד א Nun Bet Amud Aleph
and this is getting into all these questions of אפוטרופסין. apotropsin. אפוטרופסין
Apotropsin are some kind of appointed guardians. We're going to see from
the משנה mishnah and the גמרא Gemara that there are basically three
different kinds of אפוטרופוס. apotropos. There's an אפוטרופוס apotropos that the parent
appoints in their stead, presumably in the case that the parents pass
away, so that these are for minor orphans. So orphans need someone
to watch out for their business transactions and watch over the estate,
so that could be one case, the parent, the father has appointed
the אפוטרופוס. apotropos. Another possibility is an אפוטרופוס apotropos that has kind
of volunteered and just showed up and taken some responsibility over the
property. And the third possibility is that the בית דין beit din
has appointed this אפוטרופוס. apotropos. We're going to see there's some different
הלכות halakhot between different kinds of אפוטרופוס. apotropos. The משנה mishnah says:
יתומים שסמכו אצל בעל הבית, yetomim shesamkhu etzel ba'al habayit, if there
are orphans who are just hanging out at somebody's house, או שמינה
להן אביהן אפוטרופוס, o sheminah lahen avihen apotropos, or if their father
appointed for them an אפוטרופוס apotropos for after he died to watch
over the estate while they are young. Presumably, you could imagine such
a case is very apropos for our week of learning in the
ישיבה yeshiva this week, thinking about what if someone has a terminal
illness and would be survived by minor children, so that could be
a case where a person could anticipate his own death in advance
and could make arrangements in advance. It's an interesting precedent for things
like living wills and advanced directives and things. Okay, so in such
a case, אפוטרופוס חייב לעשר פירותיהם. apotropos hayyav le'aser peroteihem. The אפוטרופוס
apotropos is obligated to take מעשר, ma'aser, to take the tithes from
the produce. We're going to see that there is going to be
a מחלוקת machlokes about under what cases is that allowed and also
what's the mechanism that allows that. It seems to be a bit
of an interesting exception.
What do you mean? What's going to happen? What's he doing? What's
he doing in the first place?
Okay, so that's part of the question, which is the question we're
going to see in the גמרא Gemara is whether the יתומים yetomim
are eating this produce or whether he's just trying to sell the
produce. So we're going to see that come up in the גמרא.
Gemara.
I'm curious. I mean, don't you- aren't you supposed to take תרומות
ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot anyway?
You're supposed to take תרומה terumah and מעשר, ma'aser, but the problem
is what gave this אפוטרופוס apotropos the right to interfere or to
remove property from these יתומים? yetomim?
He's helping them out!
But he's not only helping them out- we're going to get in-
this is a מחלוקת machlokes between the תרומת הדשן Terumat Hadeshen and
the קצות Ketzot about זכין
לאדם, zakhin le'adam, זכין מאדם. zakhin me'adam. Can you take away someone's
property to do a מצוה, mitzvah, to do something that's beneficial for
them, but you're fundamentally taking away their property? So in a case
of מעשר, ma'aser, they have to do it, but without explicit permission
and with certain exemptions, particular exemptions from, it seems, from a פסוק
pasuk about תרומה terumah and מעשר, ma'aser, then you can't just take
someone's property away. It has to be someone who actually has rights
to that property. And that's really the question about an אפוטרופוס: apotropos:
what rights does an אפוטרופוס apotropos have and what rights does an
אפוטרופוס apotropos not have? We're going to see it in the גמרא.
Gemara.
Wait, but isn't he actually
a- we're going to see it in the גמרא- Gemara isn't he
actually a- what?
Like a שליח. shaliach.
So אפוטרופוס apotropos is different than a שליח. shaliach. The גמרא Gemara
in קידושין Kiddushin in the second פרק perek distinguishes three different possibilities
for how the land was apportioned when the people came into ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael with יהושע. Yehoshua. Number one is שליחות: shlikhut: making
a שליח, shaliach, some kind of an appointed or automatically appointed agent
to do your will. Number two is זכייה. zekhiyyah. זכייה Zekhiyyah is
some kind of automatically doing something beneficial for someone else, which there's
again a מחלוקת machlokes in the ראשונים: Rishonim: is זכייה מטעם שליחות
zekhiyyah mitam shlikhut or not? Is זכייה zekhiyyah part of a שליחות
shlikhut mechanism? And the third is אפוטרופוס. apotropos. אפוטרופוס Apotropos is something
different.
And it's a big question- all the ראשונים Rishonim deal with it-
there's a lot written about that. That's not for now. Okay. The
second part of the משנה, mishnah, the סיפא seifa says, אפוטרופוס שמינהו
אבי יתומים ישבע, apotropos sheminahu avi yetomim yishava, מינהו בית דין לא
ישבע. minahu beit din lo yishava. The אפוטרופוס apotropos who is appointed
by the father needs to take a שבועה shvuah that he didn't
steal property from the orphans. But if he was appointed by בית
דין, beit din, he doesn't have to take a שבועה. shvuah. אבא
שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, חילופו של דבר. hilufo shel davar. אבא
שאול Abba Shaul disagrees and we're going to see- look in רש"י,
Rashi, and it's anticipating the גמרא, Gemara, רש"י Rashi says מפני תיקון
העולם. mipnei tikkun ha'olam. Both תנאי tannai are motivated by the same
rationale, that is, we're trying to do what's best for the יתומים.
yetomim. And the question of then what kind of שבועה shvuah to
impose on the אפוטרופוס apotropos is going to depend on what psychological
factors we anticipate this אפוטרופוס apotropos is going through his head. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
ורמינהו. u'reminhu. to take תרומה truma or to take מעשר maaser from
someone else's property. Michael, this answers your question. To be someone who's
מפריש תרומה, mafrish truma, to separate tithes from someone else's produce, you
can't separate tithes from someone else's produce. You actually have to be
somewhat connected or an owner of the property and therefore not שותפים,
shutfin, not partners, business partners, co-owners.
שליח shaliach can do it.
So you can make a שליח shaliach and it's learned from a
special פסוק pasuk and it's a special kind of extension, again, not
a question for now, but thinking about who is excluded and who
is included, it seems from this ברייתא braita that אפוטרופסין apotropsin are
excluded from being able to be מפריש תרומה mafrish truma and the
גמרא Gemara רב חסדא אמר רב חסדא Rav Chisda amar Rav Chisda
לא קשיא lo kashya כאן להאכיל כאן להניח. kan le-hachil kan le-haniach.
There's a distinction between whether this is to feed the יתומים, yetomim,
and then the אפוטרופוס apotropus could be מפריש תרומה. mafrish truma. There's
a pile of fruit sitting here or a pile of grain or
whatever it is, the אפוטרופוס apotropus can separate תרומה truma and מעשר
maaser in order to actively feed the יתומים yetomim from this produce.
But להניח le-haniach to save it for 10 years from now when
they're grown up so that they'll have it in their storehouse, that's
not allowed because they'll be able to be מפריש תרומה mafrish truma
and מעשר maaser 10 years from now.
What about to sell it?
So to sell it becomes exactly the question that our גמרא Gemara
is going to deal with.
I'm sorry, can a קטן katan do תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u-maasros, no,
without a problem?
So the question of course is why do we care so much?
Aren't קטנים ktanim only חייב במצוות chayav be-mitzvot because of חינוך chinuch
anyway? So that's also part of this question which is so you're
going to allow an אפוטרופוס apotropus to have seemingly powers beyond what
this פסוק pasuk seems to imply in order to prevent קטנים ktanim
from violating what's at seemingly at worst some kind of דרבנן de-rabanan
or חינוך chinuch kind of איסור. issur. So it's a very interesting
question what exactly are we concerned with here and what's going on,
but this seems to be part of what's motivating this whole question
of אפוטרופוס, apotropus, which is קטנים ktanim need somebody to watch over
them financially and their religious growth as well and that's just part
of the environment that these יתומים, yetomim, these orphans are meant to
be growing up with. The other thing to note is what's the
mechanism behind אפוטרופסות? apotropsut? What allows this אפוטרופוס? apotropus? If this is
a פסוק pasuk that's saying אתם ולא אפוטרופסין, atem velo apotropsin, so
then אפוטרופוס apotropus can't be מפריש תרומה. mafrish truma. So how does
that work?
So רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says that this דרשה drasha is actually
just an אסמכתא asmachta and really it's only a דין דרבנן din
de-rabanan that
this principle of אתם, atem, and then the fact that an אפוטרופוס
apotropus is allowed to do it in a case of להאכיל le-hachil
is an exception based on the mechanisms of אפוטרופוס, apotropus, which is
a דרבנן de-rabanan creation anyway in order to help the יתומים. yetomim.
Other ראשונים Rishonim try to come up with other ways why it
would be an exception. We'll see תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid later talking
about selling slaves that's actually going to be an important principle, the
idea that it could be working by הפקר בית דין הפקר. hefker
beit din hefker.
Okay, it still counts what they did though, right, a קטן? katan?
If what? A קטן katan actually?
If a קטן katan takes his own produce and is מפריש תרומה,
mafrish truma, of course it would work.
No, but I'm saying אתם ולא atem velo
whatever it is, you know. No, but a קטן katan is the
owner. A קטן katan is the owner of the produce. The problem
here is whether people who are not owners of the produce would
be able to be מפריש תרומה. mafrish truma. We'll have to keep
going. And an אריס? aris? An אריס aris is a sharecropper. So
a sharecropper is someone who has, who works on the field and
perhaps even harvests all the fruit but doesn't own it. The sharecropper
is earning a salary for working on this field and that's why
he doesn't actually have a connection to the produce to be able
to be מפריש, mafrish, that's a good question. ומוכרין להן בהמה עבדים
ושפחות u-mochrin lahen behema avadim u-shfachot בתים שדות וכרמים batim sadot u-kramim
להאכיל le-hachil אבל לא להניח. aval lo le-haniach. The אפוטרופוס apotropus can
sell. והתניא? ve-hatanya?
Yeah,
the ברייתא braita supports, supports רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, sorry. והתניא אפוטרופסין
תורמין ומעשרין להאכיל אבל לא להניח. ve-hatanya apotropsin tormin u-maasrin le-hachil aval
lo le-haniach. So the ברייתא braita supports, it's interesting use of the
phrase והתניא ve-hatanya as well because it's not a question, רש"י Rashi
says בניחותא, be-nichuta, it's just as a support, not as a question.
Okay, so then the other parts of this ברייתא braita are now
going to fill up most of this דף, daf, which are include
ומוכרין להם בהמה עבדים ושפחות, u-mochrin lahem behema avadim u-shfachot, you could
sell animals and slaves, בתים שדות וכרמים batim sadot u-kramim and houses
and fields and vineyards להאכיל le-hachil to actively feed the יתומים, yetomim,
that is this money is going to provide their immediate financial support,
אבל לא להניח aval lo le-haniach but not to fill up their
trust fund for 20 years from now. מוכרין להם פירות יין שמן
וסלת, mochrin lahem peirot yayin shemen ve-solet, you could sell fruit and
wine and oil and flour, just
food להאכיל le-hachil אבל לא להניח. aval lo le-haniach.
ומוכרין להם? u-mochrin lahem? ומוכרין להם u-mochrin lahem meaning
either
you can sell, sell for them or buy for them. It's fine
both, meaning the אפוטרופוס apotropus is in charge of the financial matters
in terms of active support, but not in terms of להניח. le-haniach.
Okay, אבל לא להניח ועושין להם לולב וערבה סוכה וציצית aval lo
le-haniach ve-osin lahem lulav ve-arava sukka ve-tzitzit and the אפוטרופוס apotropus can
make for them a לולב, lulav, ערבה arava is interesting, ערבה arava
different from לולב, lulav, ערבה arava is the ערבות aravos for הושענא
רבה Hoshana Rabba which in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash they did
every day, we only do on הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba and it's
interesting to note that the ערבה arava is a מנהג, minhag, it's
not a מצוה mitzvah in the same way that some of these.
The רי"ף Rif גירסא girsa leaves out the word ערבה arava interestingly
enough. What? Why?
Meaning it wouldn't be allowed to make do it or?
Or it's not part of the paradigm that this ברייתא braita is
imposing because this
is... חינוך Chinuch anyway,
right? חינוך. Chinuch. But it's part of the question, but these the
classic examples of חינוך Chinuch are ציצית, Tzitzis, תפילין, Tefillin, and לולב
Lulav and סוכה. Sukkah. So it's interesting to note also, like, how
does that the question of חינוך Chinuch play into the question of
אפוטרופוס Apotropus as well?
תפילין Tefillin are mentioned
a little bit, one second. וכל דבר שיש לו קצבה, V'chol davar
sheyesh lo kitzvah, anything that is a fixed price or something that's
not going to be an endless cost, לאתויי שופר, l'asuyei Shofar, that
it comes to include שופר. Shofar. This is a ברייתא Beraisa that
has some emendations or parenthetic additions stuck in, it's interesting to think
about how the text came together. ולוקחים להם ספר תורה תפילין ומזוזות,
Velokchim lahem Sefer Torah, Tefillin, uMezuzos, and you can buy for them
a ספר תורה תפילין ומזוזות. Sefer Torah, Tefillin, uMezuzos. ספר תורה, Sefer
Torah,
every Jewish man has to write a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, so
to buy a ספר תורה Sefer Torah for an יתום Yosom technically
is doing a big מצוה, Mitzvah, but it's an interesting question like
why, why doesn't he just wait until he grows up? Why like—so
those are some interesting things. מהר"ם שיף Maharam Shiff goes in the
back, goes through all of these things in this ברייתא Beraisa and
tries to understand each one of these different pieces is some kind
of a חידוש. Chiddush. So there's interesting little bits and pieces there,
but some of them are a bit strange to us.
It's interesting, ספר תורה Sefer Torah for a man, really?
Well, ספר תורה Sefer Torah also back then, remember, ספר תורה Sefer
Torah means to be able to actually learn תורה. Torah. If you
didn't have a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, you weren't reading תורה. Torah.
So meaning to learn, it's not just to have a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah as a ritual object, but also to learn.
למיגרס דרדקי, L'migras dardakei, I mean, like back then you could send
them to school.
ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, so that means an education presumably is in
some sense included with that. וכל דבר שיש לו קצבה לאתויי מגילה,
V'chol davar sheyesh lo kitzvah l'asuyei Megillah, anything with a fixed price
comes to include מגילה. Megillah. מהר"ם שיף Maharam Shiff notes a מגילה
Megillah you only use once a year, twice a year, you could
borrow somebody else's? No, it's even the property could be used to
buy מצוה Mitzvah objects for the יתומים. Yesomim. It's interesting also just
think about priorities. What are we trying to say about the upbringing
and education of these orphans that these are the things that are
their priorities? ואין פוסקין עליהן צדקה, V'ein poskin aleihen Tzedakah,
you don't give צדקה Tzedakah money from their inheritance. ואין פודים עליהן
את השבויים, V'ein podin aleihen es hashvuyim, and you can't use their
money to free captives. ולא כל דבר שאין לו קצבה לאתויי תנחומי
אבלים, Velo kol davar she'ein lo kitzvah l'asuyei tanchumei aveilim, and anything
that's an unfixed price. That is, if poor people keep showing up
to this estate and say, "Oh, we're poor, please give us צדקה,"
Tzedakah, and it's a מצוה, Mitzvah, so you're doing מצוה, Mitzvah, you're
giving צדקה Tzedakah away, but then they're going to run out of
their inheritance. So it has to be something with a fixed price,
not an unfixed price. Also תנחומי אבלים, tanchumei aveilim,
whatever תנחומי אבלים tanchumei aveilim means, sending food over to a שבעה
Shiva or something like that. Also because it could be endless. It
could be every week someone is going to make a claim on
their property and say, "Yes, it's a communal need, yes, it's a
מצוה Mitzvah for them to do." Nonetheless, because it could be endless,
it's not a regular or a fixed amount, then that would deplete
their estate in such a way. It's also just interesting to think,
contrasting different kinds of מצוות, Mitzvos, which מצוות Mitzvos are יש להן
קצבה yesh lahen kitzvah and which מצוות Mitzvos are אין להן קצבה.
ein lahen kitzvah.
Does all of this typology actually say what you're allowed and not
allowed to do?
I think this is a standard clause. I'm not sure.
I mean, you can do this, that, and the other.
I don't know about that. I don't know how much right because
again, the אפוטרופוס Apotropus could be appointed by the בית דין, Beis
Din, the אפוטרופוס Apotropus could be self-appointed or picked by the יתומים
Yosomim to a certain extent. So the question of what the father—the
father's going to come up in a bit, so we'll see. אין
אפוטרופסים רשאים לדון לחוב ולזכות בנכסי יתומים. Ein apofropsim resha'im ladun lachov
velizkos b'nichsei yesomim.
So and the אפוטרופוס Apotropus cannot go to court either לחוב lachov
for their loss or לזכות lizkos or for their benefit בנכסי יתומים
b'nichsei yesomim for their property. Interesting to note. Well, so the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask, לזכות אמאי לא? Lizkos, amai lo? If
it's going to be a beneficial court case, why can't they go
to court? אלא לחוב על מנת לזכות. Ela lachov al menas lizkos.
No, it can't be something which is a detriment
in the short term which is going to have long-term benefits. But
something which is 100% totally beneficial, they could. Now again, how can
you anticipate what the court case is going to look like anyway
before you go to court? You have to decide the case. So
the ראשונים Rishonim all struggle with how to understand what this is
talking about, ultimately.
What's he supposed to do?
If there's a suit, you say, "We'll wait five years and we'll
go to court then." That's basically what you do. And again, they're
minors.
You can't bring minors to court, you can't.
Right. So and again, this is even particularly considering claims on their
property. That is, they own a field and someone comes and says,
"Actually this field belongs to me, I have a שטר." Shtar. So
they can't take this court case right now.
So what's the תבא איגרת לבית יתומים? Tavo iggeres l'veis yesomim? You
can't do it with a שבועה? Shevuah? According to here, you can't
do it ever. Okay, so that's an interesting case. So this ברייתא
Beraisa is going to be pushing up against that idea. We'll see.
ואין אפוטרופסים רשאים למכור ברחוק ולגאול בקרוב.
V'ein apofropsim resha'im limkor berachok veligol bekarov. They cannot sell
property that's far away and buy or redeem property that is close
by. ברעה, Bera'ah, they cannot sell bad property ולגאול ביפה veligol beyafah
and to buy good property. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דילמא משתדפין? Dilma
mishtadfin? Because maybe they'll become flooded, they'll become ruined, they'll be hit
by some kind of blight. So those properties, you thought it was
good property, it's going to turn out it was bad all along
anyway. Interesting to think about how in the past few דפים Dapim
we've seen a sense in חז"ל Chazal of very objective determinations of
good and bad property, and on the flip side, the understanding that
property can vary wildly in its value over time. ואין אפוטרופסים
רשאים למכור שדות וליקח עבדים. V'ein apofropsim resha'im limkor sados velikach avadim.
You could sell slaves to buy real estate. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel omer אף לא למכור עבדים וליקח שדות
af lo limkor avadim velikach sadot you cannot sell slaves and buy
fields, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, דילמא לא משפיין, dilma lo mashpyan,
because they won't produce a lot of produce according to Rashi. So
perhaps you thought that it would be a good idea to buy
a more permanent, more fixed, more productive piece of property to buy
a field, and nonetheless maybe this field isn't going to be very
productive at all, and it will end up being לחוב lachov and
the אפיטרופוס apitropos really only has a right to act for the
benefit of the יתומים yetomim seemingly.
I'm sorry, and this, which אפיטרופוס apitropos are we talking about?
This is about an אפיטרופוס, apitropos, so we're going to see. ואין
אפיטרופין רשאין להוציא עבדים לחירות, ve'ein apitropin resha'in lehotzi avadim lacherut, the
אפיטרופין apitropsin cannot free slaves, אבל מוכרין אותן לאחרים, aval mocherin otan
la'acherim, they could sell them to other people, ואחרים מוציאין אותן לחירות
ve'acherim motzi'in otan lacherut and other people could free them.
But not to buy fields.
Right, so they could sell them for cash, because cash is objectively
better than slaves, but a field is debatable, right, at least according
to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel. תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma thinks you could sell them to buy fields. Okay,
a מחלוקת machloket between Rashi and, yes?
We have a note here that it's because the lands may have
outstanding claims on them.
Right, so that's the other question which came up here as well,
which is not only that the land could be not productive but
also that there could be liens on the property. Rashi and תוספות
רי"ד Tosafot Rid have a מחלוקת machloket here about why is it
the אפיטרופין apitropsin can't sell slaves. Is it because אין גופן קנוי
להן לשחררן? ein gufan kanui lahen leshachreran? Rashi says they don't have
the right to sell them, that's just not how it works. אפיטרופין
Apitropsin don't have the right really to free slaves. They have the
right to sell slaves, they don't have the right to free slaves.
תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid says I don't understand, if they can sell
slaves they should be able to free slaves as well, but because
the whole mechanism of אפיטרופסות apitropsus only works by הפקר בית דין
הפקר, hefker beit din hefker, whatever things would be authorized by this
rabbinic paradigm, it can have rule-breaking kinds of things. So to free
a slave, even though it's fundamentally almost equivalent to selling the slave
to someone else, but that's not allowed because that's not what they
were empowered to do by the בית דין. beit din. So that
paradigm of thinking about הפקר בית דין הפקר, hefker beit din hefker,
this is בית דין beit din takes this property and says יתומים,
yetomim, you own this, we're making it הפקר, hefker, letting the אפיטרופוס
apitropos claim it and then the אפיטרופוס apitropos has the right to
do whatever he needs to do in order for your benefit, but
only limited to particular kinds of financial transactions. That's just an interesting
note.
It only applies if the בית דין beit din appoints it.
It sounds like it would only apply if it were בית דין
beit din appointed, it might be even more broadly though that הפקר
בית דין הפקר hefker beit din hefker is the underlying mechanism by
which אפיטרופסות apitropsus works. The alternative suggests it is some kind of
זכייה zechiyah or שליחות, shelichut, that somehow it's some kind of superpowered
version of זכייה. zechiyah. It could even work for some kind of
a temporary loss as long as it's a long-term gain. Okay, רבי
אומר,
Rabbi omer,
אומר אני, omer ani, and רבי Rabbi is the only תנא tanna
who ever says אומר אני, omer ani, interestingly enough, אומר אני, omer
ani, אף הוא נותן דמי עצמו, af hu noten demei atzmo, he
could even pay his own freedom, ויוצא מפני שהוא כמוכרו לו. veyotze
mipnei shehu kemochro lo. Buying your own freedom as a slave is
like someone selling the slave to someone else and the slave selling
him. So it's an interesting way to think about also the cases
we dealt with earlier with
עבדים. avadim. וצריך לחשב עמהם באחרונה, vetzarich lechashev imayhem ba'achronah, and
you have to calculate at the end how much was lost so
that the יתומים... yetomim...
or to
make
sure that everyone's being honest, for sure. Just to note how much
was spent on upkeep, how much was spent on
their foods and things like that. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban
Shimon Ben Gamliel omer, sorry, lost place. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר,
Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel omer, אינו צריך, eino tzarich, you don't have
to.
Otherwise no one's gonna want to do this.
Exactly, that's going to be the exact question, which is how much
are people wanting to do this because it's a great זכות zechut
to be either helping these people or because you'll be known in
the community as someone who's such a great guy, or because how
much are you really doing it for some other deeper reason, you
owe this guy a favor or you want them to owe you
a favor, things like that, you want the בית דין beit din
to trust you. So all of those different things are how much
do we really want to support the אפיטרופוס apitropos because אפיטרופוס apitropos
himself is supporting the יתומים. yetomim.
אין עושין אפיטרופין נשים ועבדים
וקטנים,
ein osin apitropsin nashim va'avadim
uketannim, you cannot
make an אפיטרופוס apitropos as a woman, slaves, or minors. You can't
have his wife be the אפיטרופוס. apitropos. So it's an interesting question,
well the
mother of the children, the mother of the children obviously has rights.
That's all things from כתובות, Kesubos, so in that case I'd probably
think there would be need to be some other kind of אפוטרופוס
apotropus to deal with the in-betweens in those kind of financial dealings.
It becomes complicated.
Probably more those days, you
know, women wouldn't
be viewed as being so savvy and...
Well look exactly what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi says specifically the
reason and this is an important thing to note whenever we see
נשים עבדים וקטנים Nashim, Avadim, veKetanim they're for very different reasons often.
רש"י Rashi notes נשים שאין דרכן לצאת ולבוא ולטרוח. Nashim she'ein darchan
latzeis u'lavo u'litrach. Women aren't necessarily so involved in business dealings, court
cases, going out into the market and dealing with all of those
things, so it would be difficult or inappropriate to have a woman
be an אפוטרופוס. apotropus. Now that the marketplace looks very different I
would think that this רש"י Rashi is highlighting the fact that perhaps
were this הלכה halacha to be reapplied it might be applied differently.
In looking, you know, it's been studied, it says that women are
really clueless generally, you know, when they're married about like the financials
of their husband.
I make no comment about that.
I'm saying like you know like it's unfortunate but like...
I don't know, it really depends. Family to family can be very
different and in this case...
Of course it's different but I'm saying like... Okay. Okay. ועם מינהו
אבי יתמי הרשות בידו,
Ve'im
minahu avi
yasmi hareshus beyado,
so if the father appointed these people as
אפוטרופוס, apotropus, then for sure it's fine. Meaning, as much as the
בית דין Beis Din should pick only certain people, if the father
really trusts this woman is going to be a great אפוטרופוס apotropus
for my kids or whatever, then that's of course fine because the
father has a more powerful or more
understood control over the situation.
It's his money, I mean he can do what he wants.
Exactly. Okay. ההוא אפוטרופוס. Hahu apotropus.
Are these people able to swear in court? Who?
אפוטרופסין? Apotropasin? Women, slaves, and children?
In
certain cases yeah, for sure.
Slaves, I don't know. Children, no. And slaves I'm not sure. But
women definitely in a case that a woman is involved in, of
course she can take a שבועה. shvua.
So I'm asking just this question of whether they have to swear
or not.
Right, so that's not exactly connected. There are two separate ברייתות. baraisos.
Okay.
ההוא אפוטרופוס דהוה בשיבבותיה דרבי מאיר. Hahu apotropus dehavu bishivvusei deRabbi Meir.
So there was a guy who was in רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's
town. דהוה קמזבין ארעא וזבין עבדי ולא שבקיה רבי מאיר. Dehava kamazvin
ar'a u'zavin avdi velo shavkei Rabbi Meir.
So and he was selling property and he was selling slaves and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir didn't come after... okay. אתחזי ליה בחלמא, Atlei
bechalma,
he showed up in his dream. אני להרוס ואתה לבנות, Ani leharos
ve'atah linos,
are you, you're going to destroy everything and I have to rebuild
everything?
Not exactly clear what it's talking about. אפילו הכי לא השגח Afilu
hachi lo ashbach and then even after the dream רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir didn't do anything. So why? אמר דברי חלומות לא מעלין ולא
מורידין Amar divrei chalomos lo maalin velo moridin
because dreams don't matter. Who cares about dreams? So we have a
lot of different conflicting reports about the value and meaning of dreams
throughout ש"ס. Shas. We have a lot of people, you know, in
יבמות Yevamos there are a lot of places where dreams are taken
very seriously, נדרים, Nedarim, in ברכות. Berachos. So you know, different אמוראים
Amoraim who took dreams to different levels of seriousness, it's interesting to
note רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir here didn't. Okay. הנהו בתרי דאגרי בהו
סטנא. Hanehu betrei de'igrei behu satana. There were these two guys who
were taken over by סטנא. Satan. דכל בי שמשי הוה קמינצו בהדי
הדדי Dechol bei shimshai havah kamintzu bahadei hadadi and they were always
fighting in the evening. איקלע רבי מאיר להתם עכבינהו תלתא בי שמשי
Ikla Rabbi Meir lehasam achvenhu tlata bei shimshai
so רבי Rabbi stayed by them three evenings or three perhaps it's
שבת Shabbos evenings in a row until דעבד להו שלמא ad de'avad
lehu shalma until they made peace between each other. רבי Rabbi was
able to mediate between them. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, sorry. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is able to mediate. שמעיה דקאמר ווי דאפקיה רבי מאיר
לההוא גברא מביתיה Shamei d'ka'amar vavei de'afkei Rabbi Meir lehahu gavra mibeisei
so and the סטנא Satan was very upset and he went out
of the house because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was here and he
solved the problem. The סטנא Satan can't live, the סטנא Satan brings
מחלוקת machlokes and the סטנא Satan himself cannot occupy a space where
there is שלום. shalom. So that's kind of this sense of רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it's just interesting to note רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
was a mediator between people. We know a lot of other stories
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir really going out and talking with people
and helping them with their problems as well from other גמרא. Gemara.
Okay. ההוא אפוטרופוס דהוה בשיבבותיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי Hahu apotropus dehavu
bishivvusei deRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi דהוה קמזבין ארעא וזבין תורי ולא אמר
ליה ולא מידי. Dehava kamazvin ar'a u'zavin sori velo amar lehu lei
velo midi. So there was another אפוטרופוס apotropus in the domain of
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi and he was selling
land and he was selling people's oxen, or he was selling the
oxen of the אפוטרופסין apotropsin and he didn't say anything to him.
Okay. סבר לה כרבי יוסי Savra lei keRabbi Yosi דתניא אמר רבי
יוסי מימי לא קריתי לאשתי אשתי ולשורי שורי אלא לאשתי ביתי ולשורי
שדי. Detanya amar Rabbi Yosi miyamai lo karisi leishti ishti u'leshari shori
ela leishti beisi u'leshari sadi. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi valued his wife
and ox so much that he called his wife 'my house' because
she was overseeing the entire house and he called his ox 'my
field' because the ox was in charge of the upkeep of all
of the fields. In other words, he couldn't have plowed all of
his fields without the ox. So it seems that he held the
ox in very high esteem and valued it very highly among his
possessions and
nonetheless, opinion of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, so it sounds like in
nonetheless רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi he did not
object to this אפוטרופוס apotropus selling the ox, oxen. Okay. הנהו יתמי
דהוו סמכי גבי ההיא סבתא. Hanehu yasmei dehavu samchei gabei hahu sabta.
There were these יתומים yetomim hanging out with this older woman. הוה
להו תורתא שקלה וזבנה מינייהו. Havay lehu torta, shakla ve-zabna mineihu. So
they had this ox, she sold it, she took it and sold
it. אתו קרובים לקמיה דרב נחמן Atu krovim lekamey derav Nachman אמרו
ליה מאי
עבידתי דזבינה.
amru lei
mai avidtai dezavina. So they, the קרובים, krovim, the relatives came and
said like, "What did you do? Why did you sell the ox?"
אמר להו יתומים שנסמכו אצל בעל הבית. Amar lehu yetomim she-nismachu etzel
baal ha-bayis. So she said like, "No, if it's the case of
יתומים yetomim who are סומכים אצל בעל הבית, somchim etzel baal ha-bayis,
it's exactly the case from our משנה Mishnah that יתומים yetomim could
pick out this אפוטרופוס apitropas and she's acting in their best interest
to sell the ox in order to support them." Okay. תנן. Tnan.
So that's the case she quotes from the משנה. Mishnah. והא איקור
בירשותא דלוקח. Ve-ha ikar bi-reshusa de-lokeach. איקור. Ikar. And it got more
expensive in the property of the person who bought it. What happened?
She had sold the ox and then the ox went up in
value. So that's the question: What is now beneficial or what could
be done to help? Could they get more money back? Something like
that. So that's the
question. ועדא לא נקיטי דמי. Ve-ada lo nekiti damei. And they didn't
yet pay the money. Right, that's the point. They had passed over
the ox to these people. They were going to get the money
a week later and then the price of oxen had gone up.
So that's the question. אמר להו אם כן הנהו דרב חנילאי בר
אידי אמר שמואל דאמר רב חנילאי בר אידי אמר שמואל דזבני רב
חנילאי נכסי יתומים הרי הן כהקדש ולא מקני אלא בכספא. Amar lehu
im ken hanu de-rav Chanilai bar Idi amar Shmuel de-amar rav Chanilai
bar Idi amar Shmuel de-zabni rav Chanilai nichsei yetomim harei hen ke-hekdesh
ve-lo makni ela be-chaspa. The property of orphans, the property that is
being administered by an אפוטרופוס, apitropas, is comparable to הקדש. hekdesh. In
what sense? In that it can only be bought with money. That
is when the property is passed over, when the ox is passed
over, we don't evaluate the transaction until the money changes hands. This
is a מחלוקת machlokes between רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan and ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish in terms of regular sales. Do we say מעות קונות
maos konos or do we say דאינו נקנה אלא במשיכה? de-eino nikneh
ela be-meshicha? When I buy a book and I pay the bookseller
ten dollars and then he gives me the book and I pick
up the book, so when did the transaction take place? When I
paid the money or when I picked up the book? So usually
we would think, we normally
think, מטלטלין metaltelin can only really be bought by actually taking ownership
of the object. With a שור shor you have to pull the
שור. shor. נכסי דיתמי Nichsei de-yatmei for their benefit, we're going to
also allow it to work like הקדש, hekdesh, that is that it
could only be bought by money. We're going to see it actually
plays out for the יתומים's yetomim benefit in both ways. Yeah, you
have a question?
Is there an ענין inyan if they made this contract with a
provider over the course of the year for like, to get like
futures? If the price rises or
falls, the יתומים yetomim
always gets the benefit.
Right, so that's something similar. Exactly the same kind of principle. The
יתומים yetomim is like הקדש hekdesh in what way? That we rig
the system that when we say אינו נקנה אלא בכספא eino nikneh
ela be-chaspa it really means we take whatever's the best deal for
their side. That is one of the ways we protect יתומים, yetomim,
we protect orphans is by giving them the best deal always.
But wouldn't people be less likely to buy things then from the
יתומים? yetomim?
So that's maybe a question. Maybe that's why they need an אפוטרופוס
apitropas who's a good negotiator or something like that. People still want
to buy the field. The question is then how do you deal
with
that? So okay. חמרא דרבנא עוקבא יתמי משכוה בארבעה ארבעה. Chamra de-rabna
Ukva yatmei mashchuha be-arba'ah arba'ah. So they were selling the wine of
רבנא עוקבא Rabna Ukva from the orphans and they did משיכה meshicha
when it was worth four per barrel. Okay, ואיקר ve-ikar and it
got more expensive וקם בשיתה שיתה ve-kam be-shita shita and then it
was worth six per barrel. אתו לקמיה דרב נחמן אמר להו הנהו
דרב חנילאי בר אידי דאמר רב חנילאי בר אידי אמר שמואל נכסי
יתומים הרי הן כהקדש ולא מקני אלא בכספא. Atu lekamey de-rav Nachman
amar lehu hanu de-rav Chanilai bar Idi de-amar rav Chanilai bar Idi
amar Shmuel nichsei yetomim harei hen ke-hekdesh ve-lo makni ela be-chaspa. So
they could only be bought with money and therefore you give whatever
the benefit and it'll be sold at the price of six rather
than the price of four, which is a lot of money. You
know, if you sell a hundred barrels of wine, that's a hundred
fifty percent increase in the profit or whatever. משכו פירי מיתמי. Mashchu
pirya mi-yatmei. If you pulled the fruit from the יתומים, yetomim, that
is you did the משיכה meshicha part, so someone else took acquisition
of the property of the יתומים. yetomim.
ואיקר Ve-ikar and then it got more expensive. היינו דרב חנילאי בר
אידי. Hainu de-rav Chanilai bar Idi. That's the case that רב חנילאי
בר אידי Rav Chanilai bar Idi said. זול. Zol. What if it
got cheaper? לא יהא כח הדיוט חמור מהקדש. Lo yehei koach hedyot
chamur me-hekdesh. So don't let the power of a regular sale, that
is when it's קונה במשיכה, koneh be-meshicha, be worse than הקדש. hekdesh.
And we mean הקדש, hekdesh, we mean יתומים. yetomim. That is, give
the יתומים yetomim the best deal that they can between כסף kesef
or משיכה. meshicha. In this case, the משיכה meshicha case is better,
so give them the משיכה meshicha case. It's kind of like מה
כח בית דין יפה. ma koach beis din yafeh.
Excuse me. Okay, חמור כהקדש. chamur ke-hekdesh. משכו להו פירי ליתמי. Mashchu
lehu pirya le-yatmei. What if the יתומים yetomim are buying the ox
and they pull the ox? Okay, ליתמי ואיקר לא יהא כח הדיוט
חמור מהקדש. Le-yatmei ve-ikar lo yehei koach hedyot chamur me-hekdesh. So if
it got more expensive once they had done משיכה, meshicha, then we
should still say fine, so it's they benefited, they should still pay
the lower price. זול Zol and what if the price went lower?
סבר מינה היינו דרב חנילאי בר אידי אמר רב
חנילאי בר אידי.
Savar minah hainu de-rav Chanilai bar Idi
amar rav Chanilai bar Idi. So that's also like the case of
רב חנילאי בר אידי Rav Chanilai bar Idi in reverse that we
say we give them from the time that they pay cash even
when they're selling it as
when they're buying it as well. So exactly your question, which is
there are times when the יתומים *yetomim* are going to need food
right now, they need this cow, they need to buy something, so
people will be hesitant to sell them if they know they're going
to lose out if the price fluctuates. Now, ask why don't you
just pay cash right then when you do the transaction? But that's
a separate question. You know, in the nature, maybe people didn't have
cash or whatever, and they won't have it because that so we
should say we shouldn't apply this principle universally because it's going to
end up resulting people won't want to do business with the יתומים
*yetomim*. איבעיא להו עד יהבי זוזי *Iba'ya lehu ad yahavi zuzei* because
they'll wait until they bring the money. אי יהבי יתמי זוזי אפירי
*Ei yahavi yatmi zuzei apirei*, זו לא יהיה כח הדיוט חמור מהקדש
*zo lo yehei koach hedyot chamur mehekdesh*, סבר מינה היינו דרב חנילאי
בר אידי *savar minah hainu deRav Chanilai bar Idi*. Okay, so that
meaning, so then rather we should still say like the previous way,
that still you should say מה כח הדיוט חמור מן ההקדש *mah
koach hedyot chamur min hahekdesh* about if they had brought, they paid
cash for the cow and in first, they had paid cash first,
so that kind of case then it would work out. Okay. אמר
ליה רב שישא בריה דרב אידי הא רעה לדידהו דאתו למימר להו
נשרפו חטיכם בעליה *Amar lei Rav Shisha brei deRav Idi ha ra'ah
ledidhu de'atu lemeimar lehu nisrefu chitechem ba'aliya*. No, so then what could
happen? If they pay cash first and then the price fluctuates, well
what's going to happen? The claim that always happens if you pay
cash before you get the object, the person always has this claim
נשרפו חטיכם בעליה *nisrefu chitechem ba'aliya*. The wheat I was selling you,
it burned up in your attic. As if to say, you paid
cash and then you go and check on the property and vanished,
gone, burned up, destroyed. So what happened? The person always can claim
it was destroyed as right after I sold it to you. So
tough cookies, you know, and there's no way to get out of
that kind of a system. That's why we try to avoid that's
always the claim against suggesting that you should be able to buy
something with cash. The claim is that you should actually be able
to have the property in your hand, because otherwise נשרפו חטיכם בעליה
*nisrefu chitechem ba'aliya*. Okay. יהבי להו זוזי יתמי אפירי *Yahavi lehu zuzei
yatmi apirei*. What if they paid cash for the fruits? אי הכי
לא יהיה כח הדיוט חמור מן ההקדש *ei hachi lo yehei koach
hedyot chamur min hahekdesh*, זו סבר מינה היינו דרב חנילאי בר אידי
*zo savar minah hainu deRav Chanilai bar Idi*. אמר ליה רב שישא
בריה דרב אידי הא רעה לדידהו דזימנין דמצטרכי לזוזי *Amar lei Rav
Shisha brei deRav Idi ha ra'ah ledidhu dezimnin demitztrachi lezuzei* and they
won't have it because of that, so we
should say we shouldn't apply this and they won't have it because
and they'll wait until they can give the fruits, and that's going
to also impact them. אמר רב אשי אנא ורב כהנא חתמינא אשטרא
דאימיה דזעירא יתמי דמזבנא ארעא לכרגא בלא אכרזתא דאמרי נהרדאי לכרוזא ולמזוני
ולקבורה מזבנינן בלא אכרזתא *Amar Rav Ashi ana veRav Kahana chatmina ashtara
de'imme deZ'ira yatmei demizbana ar'a lechagra belo achrazata de'amrei Nehardai lechraza ulemezonei
ulekvurah mazbeninan belo achrazata*. So רב אשי *Rav Ashi* said: I and
רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* signed on a שטר *shatar* to sell a
field to pay a tax because we didn't wait the amount of
time you need to do אכרזתא *achrazata*. אכרזתא *Achrazata* is making a
big announcement, we're selling the field of the יתומים *yetomim*, we need
the best deal we can get and waiting out for someone who's
willing to pay a higher price. They said we didn't wait for
it. Why? Because these things you can do without אכרזתא *achrazata*. The
נהרדאי *Nehardai* say for the taxes or for food or for a
burial plot,
so those things you can sell without אכרזתא *achrazata*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
notes it's interesting to note considering the fact of קבורה *kvurah* seems
obvious. Obviously you're going to buy a burial plot immediately and not
delay the funeral, so it must be something else about the קבורה
*kvurah*. What if you bought a burial plot on a loan and
then the question of about paying back the loan? So that's תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* says the seemingly obvious case is too obvious to be
listed in this הלכה halacha *halacha*. Okay. עמרם צבא אפוטרופוס apotropas, דיתמי
הוה *Amram Tzeva apotropos deyitmi havah*. So this guy עמרם צבא *Amram
Tzeva* was an אפוטרופוס apotropas, *apotropos*. אתו קרובים לקמיה דרב נחמן *Atu
krovim lekamei deRav Nachman*. אמרי ליה קא לביש ומכסי מיתמי *Amrei lei
ka lavesh umachsei miyatmei*.
He's buying fancy clothes and stuff from the property of the יתומים
*yetomim*. אמר להו כהאי דלישתמיעא מילא קאכיל ושתי מדידיהו ולא אמרו אימור
מציאה אשכח *Amar lehu kehai dileshtami'ah meila kachil vishatei mididhu velo amru
eimur mitzia eshkach*. No, no, no, maybe he won't be he's eating
and drinking from his own. Don't say maybe he found a very
expensive lost object. We give him the benefit of the doubt. We
have to give the אפוטרופוס apotropas. *apotropos* a benefit of the doubt.
Okay. והא קא מפסיד *Veha ka mafsid*. But isn't he then losing
all the property of the יתומים *yetomim* if he's spending carefree? Okay,
and that's a big problem. So he said: אמר להו אייתו לי
סהדי דמפסיד ומסלקינן ליה *Amar lehu aitu li sahadei demafsid umasalkinan lei*.
So bring me witnesses that he actually is losing their property and
I'll take him away, I'll remove his powers as אפוטרופוס apotropas? *apotropos*.
It means bring me the proof. We have to give the אפוטרופוס
apotropas. *apotropos* a benefit of the doubt presumably because we want the
אפוטרופוס apotropas *apotropos* to keep a job. Who's going to have this
incredible responsibility to care for these יתומים *yetomim* unless they get certain
legal benefits? Okay. דאמר רב הונא חברין משמיה דרב אפוטרופוס apotropas דמפסיד
מסלקינן ליה *De'amar Rav Huna chavrin mishmei deRav apotropos demafsid mesalkinan lei*.
So an אפוטרופוס apotropas *apotropos* who loses the property of the יתומים
*yetomim*, we remove him. דאיתמר אפוטרופוס דמפסיד רב הונא אמר רב מסלקינן
ליה דבי רבי שילא אמרי לא מסלקינן ליה והלכתא מסלקינן ליה *De'itmar
apotropos demafsid Rav Huna amar Rav mesalkinan lei debei Rebbi Shila amrei
lo mesalkinan lei vehilchata mesalkinan lei*. So we have actually a מחלוקת
machloket אמוראים *machloket amoraim* but we פסקן pasken *pasken* that you take
him away.
Fine. An אפוטרופוס who is appointed by the father of the orphans
takes this oath.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? אי לאו דאית ליה הנאה מיניה, I lav
de'is lei hana'ah minei, לא הוה ליה אפוטרופוס. lo hava lei apotropas.
If he didn't get any הנאה hana'ah from this deal of being
the אפוטרופוס, then he never would've done it to begin with. ומשום
שבועה לא אתי לאמנויי. u'mishum shvua lo ati l'amnuyei. And then if
he's forced to take a שבועה shvua at the end, then the
negatives are going to outweigh the positives and he's not going to
want to do it. מינוהו בית דין לא ישבע. minuhu beis din
lo yishava. So if he was appointed by, sorry, the opposite. ומשום
שבועה לא אתי לאמנויי. u'mishum shvua lo ati l'amnuyei. He has a
benefit from this transaction. So the fact that he'll have to take
a שבועה shvua is not going to deter him from agreeing to
the deal. The father must have made a special deal, paid him
in advance, something to make him want to do it. And therefore
we can make him take a שבועה shvua and it's going to
be okay because he'll still agree to do it anyway.
When does he take the שבועה? shvua?
At the end, when the children grow up, he takes a שבועה
shvua that he didn't steal property.
Right, that he didn't steal. Right, that he didn't benefit.
Well, he—that he didn't get anything inappropriately.
Well, he gets some kind of a benefit, exactly, but the שבועה
shvua is to ensure that he
doesn't—he's some kind of a שומר shomer to a certain extent. He's
a שומר shomer with extra special powers, right? He can sell property.
A regular שומר shomer just watches the property. So it's kind of
an interesting
exemption, but something like a שבועת השומרים. shvoat hashomrim. מינוהו בית דין
לא ישבע. minuhu beis din lo yishava. But if he was appointed
by בית דין, beis din, he doesn't take an oath. Why? מילתא
בעלמא הוא דעביד לבי דינא. milta b'alma hu d'avid le'bei dina. He's
just doing a favor for
בית דין. beis din. ואי רמית עליה שבועה, ve'i ramit lei shvua,
אתי לאמנויי. ati l'amnuyei. He'll resist, he won't want to be the
אפוטרופוס, so you'll have a hard time finding someone who wants to
be an אפוטרופוס. So this is saying, how do you get someone
to be an אפוטרופוס? You pay them. But בית דין beis din
doesn't pay people to be אפוטרופוס. Therefore a בית דין beis din
appointed אפוטרופוס is going to be less inclined to be a benefit
to the children. It's interesting to consider how courts nowadays think about
foster care with relatives, with non-relatives, things like that, the certain amount—how
much do you provide incentives to people to have a positive impact
on raising these orphans. Okay. אבא שאול אומר חילוף הדברים. Abba Shaul
omer chiluf hadvarim. So how can אבא שאול Abba Shaul disagree with
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and think it's actually totally the opposite
way? מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? מינוהו בית דין ישבע בההיא הנאה דקא
נפיק עליה קלא דאינש מהימן הוא. minuhu beis din yishava be'hahi hana'ah
d'ka nafik lei kala d'inish meheiman hu. So the fact that if
you're appointed by בית דין, beis din, then you become publicly known
as a trustworthy person that the בית דין beis din trusted you
to oversee the property. Okay. דהא סמכו עליה בית דין. d'ha samchu
lei beis din. The court trusts you. ומשום שבועה לא אתי לאמנויי
מינהון. u'mishum shvua lo ati l'amnuyei minehon. So the fact that we
force him to take a שבועה shvua is not going to deter
him because now he's going to have a great public reputation. אבי
יתומים לא ישבע מילתא בעלמא הוא דעביד לההוא גברא ואי רמית עליה
שבועה אתי לאמנויי. avi yetomim lo yishava milta b'alma hu d'avid l'hahu
gavra ve'i ramit lei shvua ati l'amnuyei. But if he's appointed by
the father, he's just doing a favor for someone who's now dead.
So you're doing a favor for a dead person, then that's not
going to really build your reputation the same way that being appointed
by the court is going to have a positive impact on your
reputation. אמר רב חנן בר אמי אמר שמואל הלכתא כאבא שאול. Amar
Rav Chanan bar Ami amar Shmuel hilchata k'Abba Shaul. So here רב
חנן בר אמי Rav Chanan bar Ami says in the name of
שמואל Shmuel the הלכה halacha is like אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. If
you look in the רי"ף, Rif, there's actually some issues. The רי"ף
Rif seems to not פסקן pasken like אבא שאול—it's Abba Shaul a,
oh, sorry, the רי"ף Rif does פסקן like אבא שאול. Abba Shaul.
תוספות brings a question, but רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov and the question of the next ברייתא baraita seems to contradict
אבא שאול's Abba Shaul opinion, and so therefore maybe the הלכה halacha
should go against אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. Sorry. The next ברייתא: baraita:
תניא רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר זה וזה ישבע. Tanya Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov omer zeh vezeh yishava. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov says against both opinions in our משנה mishnah and this
ברייתא, baraita, he says actually both of them have to take a
שבועה, shvua, whether appointed by the father or appointed by בית דין.
beis din. הלכה כדבריו. Halacha kidvarav. And his ברייתא baraita says the
הלכה is like him. So that's the question that תוספות is dealing
with. תני רב תחליפא בר מערבא קמיה דרבי אבהו אפוטרופוס שמינוהו אבי
יתומים ישבע מפני שהוא נושא שכר. Tani Rav Tachlifa bar Ma'arava kammai
de'Rabbi Abbahu apotropas sheminuhu avi yetomim yishava mipnei shehu nosei sachar. So
the reason why the אפוטרופוס who's appointed by the father takes a
שבועה shvua is he is a נושא שכר, nosei sachar, he's a
שומר שכר, shomer sachar, a שומר, shomer, he's really a שומר, shomer,
he's paid, he has a paid benefit. Question of whether the גירסא
girsa is נושא שכר. nosei sachar. אמר ליה אנת אייתי כבא וכליא
ליה אלא אימא מפני שהוא כנושא שכר. Amar lei ant aitei kava
u'chelei lei ela eima mipnei shehu kenosei sachar. He's not a שומר
שכר, shomer sachar, he's like a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. He gets
a certain amount of benefit from this transaction. There's a lot more
to be said about this דף daf for sure. In some of
the תוספותים, Tosafotim, there
are all sorts of interesting topics, take a look in the ר"ן,
Ran, and actually there's a fantastic מחלוקת between the ראב"ד Ra'avad and
the רמב"ם Rambam on the דפי הרי"ף, dapei ha'Rif, really about how
אפוטרופוס gets involved with all these questions, all other sorts of things.
Really a very jam-packed דף. daf. We'll have to stop here. I
have to go downstairs.
But with that, pick up with the next משנה mishnah tomorrow.